Should I buy travel insurance for my
parents from India or from the US?
This is one question we get regularly but the
frequency of these questions increases
as summer approaches because that is when most
Indian parents visit the US.  Our
parents visited the US last year and we
have the same questions.  We researched, spoke to
our friends who have been in the US for more than
a decade and thanks to all of you who
follow us on Instagram.  We were also able to
ask a ton of questions to an insurance
expert at Visitors Coverage to make a
decision.  And in today's video I'm going
to break down the differences of buying
travel insurance for parents from
India vs the US.  Hi everyone.  I'm
Priya from It's OKR and if you're
new today.  It's OKR is a content
platform for South Asian immigrants and
we aim to educate, entertain and empower them.
Before I Start Sharing What We
Found I wanted to quickly explain the
process of research for this video.  So, of
course, we relied heavily on our own past
experiences, the experiences of our
friends and our community, and our
conversations with the insurance expert
administrators coverage.  But we didn't want any
bias to cloud our judgment.  So we but a
$20 subscription for Gemini Advanced
and use their deep research tools to get the
most comprehensive findings.  If You Are
Interested We Will Leave The Research
Document In The Description So That
Everyone Can Go Through It.  So without any further
delay, let's get started.  We will discuss
the difference between purchasing insurance
from India versus the US based on a few key
parameters.  Those parameters are
number one, PPO network and cost
management.  Number two, health care provider
acceptance and billing, number three,
familiarity, number four, coverage depth.  Number
five, customer service and claims handling.
Number one, PPO network and cost
management.  First, let's understand
what the PPO network is.  Think of it like
a list of hospitals and doctors that
have agreements with the insurance company.
These hospitals have no insurance and many of them even
agree to a negotiated rate
for the same services that would typically cost
thousands without insurance.  Two of the
biggest PPO networks in the USR
United Healthcare PPO and First
Health PPO networks.  Now if you get an
insurance from India, the policy does not have
a US PPO network.  Ideally, you can still go to
any hospital you want in
the US, but here's the catch.  Most US
hospitals won't be familiar with Indian
insurance companies.  So, you won't receive the
negotiated price that a US insurance
policy holder would have and the hospital will
ask you to pay the entire amount out of
pocket.  Then you will have to file a claim
with the insurance company back in India, and
hope they reimburse you.  That means a huge
payment up front for you and then a huge
hustle of paperwork and the long wait up front hearing whether or
not you will get your money
back from the insurance company.  In the US,
however, because the insurance you buy will be
associated with the PPO network, the
hospitals know the insurance and have
already agreed on negotiated prices for
your medical service.  The best part is some
of them can build the insurance company
directly.  You won't have to pay a huge
bill out of your own pocket and then hope you
will get reimbursements.  Number two, health care
provider acceptance and billing.  Similar
to What I Said About PPO Networks: The
Willingness of US Health Care
Providers.  That is hospitals and
doctors to accept travel insurance
from India based companies is relatively
lower.  Why the US health care system is more accustomed
to dealing with domestic
insurance companies, which often leads to
simple direct billing arrangements.  Many
health care providers in the US may not be
familiar with Indian insurance
companies.  This can be challenging because then
you may need to proactively inquire with
hospitals and doctors about their
willingness to accept insurance from
an Indian company and build them directly
in India.  Which in turn can introduce
uncertainty and delays in getting the care
our parents deserve.  Time zone and
language barriers are also factors to be
considered.  Number three, familiarity.
What do I mean when I say familiarity
in the context of buying insurance.
Most Indian families have a family
insurance agent who has been with us for
decades.  Sure some of them have sold bogus
policies to our father from time to time.
But the best part is that they are accessible.
We Know Who to Reach Out to When the Need
Arises.  One call and the insurance agent
will be at our homes to explain multiple
different policies as compared to buying it
from the US that requires you to research a lot
and watch videos like this to make up
your mind but mostly the familiarity ends
after the purchase the issue of filing a claim
for reimbursement hospitals not
accepting Indian insurance still remains
number four coverage options and depth
largely there are two types of coverage
options when it comes to insurance number
one fixed coverage and limited coverage number
two comprehensive coverage.  As the name suggests,
limited plans have limited coverage.  That
is covers less instances to a lesser
extent.  While this is great for someone who
is younger and only once basic coverage.  This
is not ideal for those of us who
want to get coverage for their parents who are
older and could need more medical coverage.
Comprehensive coverage plans cover a lot
of instances, but a lot of them cover
acute onset of pre-existing conditions,
and have added benefits related to travel
disruption, such as trip cancellation, loss of
baggage, etc.  Comprehensive coverage plans
cover a lot more instances, especially when it comes
to what many of us are concerned
about, treatment of pre-existing
conditions and acute on set of pre-
existing conditions.  Plus comprehensive
plans also include some unique benefits
that we never considered such as emergency
transportation to the nearest hospital,
lost stole, passport, border entry
protection, etc.  There are some
comprehensive plans in the US that cover
pre-existing conditions as well as acute ones.
However, many Indian companies
primarily offer fixed coverage plans, which may have
lower maximum limits and may
not provide adequate financial
protection in the event of an emergency in
the US.  Also, these plans often come with age
restrictions, potentially limiting their
availability for older parents.  There are
obviously some comprehensive plans in
India that offer coverage of around
$1,000 but the premiums are very high.
Pro tip, whether you are buying insurance
in India or the US please look for
insurance that is comprehensive in
nature.  Since we are on the topic of pre-
existing conditions, I want to share a
couple of things.  Many US-based travel
insurance plans offer coverage for acute
hospitalizations of up to a certain age.  Typically
around 70 to 79 years.  Some plans also
provide coverage for pre-existing
conditions that gradually worsen over time such as
diabetes and hypertension.  Policies
offering broader coverage for pre-existing
conditions will most likely have higher
premiums and specific waiting periods
before the coverage becomes effective.  It is
essential to carefully review the policy wording regarding
pre-existing
conditions to understand the scope and
limitations of coverage.  Some of the better
comprehensive plans in the US are
Atlas America, Patriot America and
Visitors Protect for pre-existing
conditions.  You can buy this or any other based
on your requirements from visitors
coverage.  We will drop the link in the
description below.  Last Year We Boated
Atlas America for Our Parents.  Number
five, customer service and claims handling.
Hood you think is better in this case.  If you are
in the US, it is always a little less hassle to
handle claims etc. than doing so in
India while you are in the US.  Many US
insurers offer 24-hour customer support which can be
invaluable during medical
emergencies that occur at any time.  For
travel insurance purchased in India,
claims processing is frequently
handled in India itself.  This can lead
to delays and administrative
complexities when trying to
communicate from the US due to
significant time zone differences and
process differences between the US
hospitals and the Indian insurance
company.  Customer support may primarily be
available during the India business hours which can be
inconvenient for someone in the
US needing immediate assistance.  Apart
from these main factors, there are some
secondary parameters that you can compare such as
regulations around insurance in
both countries, renewability or cancellation
policies etc.  Here is the table that will give
you a good overview of all the
differences.  To summarize based on the
comparative analysis I would strongly
recommend that you should purchase travel
insurance from a US based company for
your Indian parents visiting the US. The
advantages offered by US based
insurers include stronger regulatory
protection, better acceptance by the US
health providers, more comprehensive
coverage options, access to PPO networks
and more convenient customer service and
pleasing handling. Significantly outweigh the
potential cost savings of opting in an
Indian based policy and that was the video
guys I leave our entire research search
material in the description below along with all
of the sources for you to refer to.  And I will also
link some great insurance
plans that you can purchase from Visitors
Coverage.  We work with them earlier and it has been
a great experience to be
honest.  We purchase it for our parents and
in loss to.  However, please do read all the
details before purchasing any insurance.
And remember if things are going your way it's okay man because they will eventually turn around.
This is Priya signing off until
next time.  Have a great day.